Joel Oppenheimer Papers 1990.0056
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
- Series III: Prose, undated, 1947-1988
  - Non-Fiction Articles
    - "Down on the Farm" - TSS of baseball article for New York Magazine, with correspondence and notes, 1979 (Box 19:1257)
    - Articles/ Columns by JO (some Village Voice?), ca. 1980 (Box 19:1258)
    - Articles/Columns by JO (publications unknown), ca. 1977-1985? (Box 19:1259)
    - TSS Carbons of Village Voice columns, 1981 (Box 19:1260)
    - Copies of Village Voice columns, 1981-1983 (Box 19:1261)
    - TSS of book reviews, other prose articles, ca. 1983-1984 (Box 19:1262)
    - Copies of articles by JO ( Ararat, New Hampshire Profiles, Options, Gallery), ca. 1983-1984 (Box 19:1263)
    - TSS Carbons of articles for Village Voice, Ararat, New Hampshire Profiles, 1983-1985 (Box 19:1264)
    - TSS Carbons of Village Voice articles, ca. 1984-1985 (Box 19:1265)
    - TSS Articles on Baseball, ca. 1985 (Box 19:1266)
    - TSS of Columns for New Hampshire Times, 1985-1986 (Box 19:1267)
    - Copies of articles in New Hampshire Times (includes letters published in response to JO), 1985-1986 (Box 19:1268)
    - Copies of articles by JO ( ACUCAA Bulletin, Daily News Magazine), 1986 (Box 19:1269)
    - TSS Articles and Columns (includes Village Voice obituary for Eugene Rachlis, some TSS may be for speeches), 1986-1987 (Box 19:1270)
  - Interviews and Lectures
    - Poetry, "The Ecology of the Soul" - proofs of lectures by JO, correspondence from David Landrey, 1983 (Box 19:1271)
    - "Language vs. Poetry" - transcript of JO lecture (draft TSS with corrections by JO), ca. 1983-1985 (Box 19:1272)
    - Transcript TSS of JO interviews by Bill Sylvester, 1985 (Box 19:1273)
    - TSS of commencement address by JO for New England College (multiple drafts), 1985-1986 (Box 19:1274)
    - Transcript TSS of JO interview by Chris Beach, 1986-1988 (Box 19:1275)
    - TSS "About New Forms" - Lecture given by JO at The Poetry Project, 4/9/88, 1988 (Box 19:1276)
- Series IV: Notes and Ephemera, undated, 1925-1986
  - Ephemera--Personal notes and records
    - Two sketch illustrations (poor quality - not identified), undated (Box 20:1277)
    - High School Football Program, JO's ID card at age 19, 1946, 1949 (Box 20:1278)
    - Cornell University Scholarship Information, ca. 1947 (Box 20:1279)
    - Black Mountain College Ephemera - flyers and catalogs, including flyer for play Cuchulain in which JO appeared, 1949-1952 (Box 20:1280)
    - Black Mountain College - Event Announcement Cards (layout by JO? - marked as Sad Devil Press), 1952 (Box 20:1281)
    - 1 pc. painting, 1 pc. drawing by Fielding Dawson, 1952 (Box 20:1282)
    - JO's Thanksgiving Menu (in French), 1958 (Box 20:1283)
    - Poetry Notebook - MSS version of "The Crooked Will," JO's reading list for fall 1959 (Box 20:1284)
    - Two Notebooks - largely empty, one poem in MSS, undated (Box 20:1285)
    - Notebook - notes and philosophical journal, 1959 (Box 20:1286)
    - Financial Records (3 pieces), 1959-1961 (Box 20:1287)
    - Income Tax Records, Court Papers, Insurance Records, 1960-1966 (Box 20:1288)
    - Galleys and notes from JO's work as editor of Kulchur 5, ca. 1961 (Box 20:1289)
    - Clippings regarding Poetry Readings by JO, 1961-1967 (Box 20:1290)
    - Program for Ezra Pound's 78th Birthday Dinner, includes transcript of readings by JO and others, 1963 (Box 20:1291)
    - Adult Education Brochure promoting seminar involving JO and LeRoi Jones, 1963-1964 (Box 20:1292)
    - Personal notes detailing JO's sexual relationships, ca. 1964 (Box 20:1293)
    - Personal notes regarding Tarot Readings (questions JO's relationship to "D"), ca. 1964 (Box 20:1294)
    - Notes and Fragments in TSS, ca. 1965? (Box 20:1295)
    - News clippings regarding JO reading interrupted by police officer, 1966 (Box 20:1296)
    - Associated Council on the Arts Conference Materials (clipping details JO's role as guest speaker), 1966-1967 (Box 20:1297)
    - Notes - JO's rules for imaginary board game on dating (see Gilmore, Don't Touch the Poet, p. 137-39), ca. 1967? (Box 20:1298)
    - Notes and outlines, including lettering designs, ca. 1966-1968 (Box 20:1299)
    - Notes, doodles, floor plan sketches, ca. 1968 (Box 20:1300)
    - "Bulleting Board Nonsense", and notes on 1968 election, ca. 1968 (Box 20:1301)
    - Clippings regarding End of the Road (film in which JO had cameo) and The Great White Hope, includes part of shooting schedule for End of the Road, 1968-1969 (Box 20:1302)
    - Clippings/ Articles in which JO is mentioned or quoted, 1968-1969 (Box 20:1303)
    - Teachers and Writers Collaborative (budgeting, correspondence), 1969 (Box 20:1304)
    - Teachers and Writers Collaborative (notes, clippings, correspondence), 1969 (Box 20:1305)
    - Student Publications relating to Teachers and Writers Collaborative, 1969 (Box 20:1306)
    - Clippings related to Charles Olson's funeral, includes correspondence, TSS of "The Polish Cavalry", 1970 (Box 20:1307)
    - Financial Records and Travel Receipts, ca. 1970 (Box 20:1308)
    - Fliers and Mailers for Environment! action group (includes TSS drafts by JO), ca. 1970 (Box 20:1309)
    - Baseball Ephemera, notes, fantasy lineups, ca. 1970 (Box 20:1310)
    - Three Notebooks (mostly names and addresses), ca. 1970? (Box 20:1311)
    - "Bold as Dice" - copy of article from Fourth Estate, includes section on JO, reprints The Love Bit, 1972 (Box 20:1312)
    - Poetry Project Newsletter (incomplete), 1972-1976 (Box 20:1313)
    - Schedule for TV appearance by JO (CAPS Public Service TV, appeared with Audre Lord and Jayne Cortez), 1975 (Box 20:1314)
    - Teaching Materials - Exercise based on "The Artist" by William Carlos Williams, ca. 1970-1980 (Box 20:1315)
    - NEA Grant application materials, 1975-1976 (Box 20:1316)
    - Copies of articles that mention JO (JO not main focus), 1958, 1977-1986 (Box 20:1317)
    - Photos of JO (professional quality - B/W), ca. 1978 (Box 20:1318)
    - Notes, Receipts, and Financial Records, 1980-1982 (Box 20:1319)
    - Promotional flyers for JO appearances and publications, ca. 1980-1985 (Box 20:1320)
    - Receipts for book sales of JO's books, royalty statements, 1982-1983 (Box 21:1321)
    - "Complete Dossier" - folder containing copies of resume, ca. 1983 (Box 21:1322)
    - Copy of dissertation abstract about JO by David Thibodaux at Kansas State University, 1983 (Box 21:1323)
    - Teaching Materials - quotes from Blues songs selected by JO, program for workshop "On the Blues", ca. 1984 (Box 21:1324)
    - Ephemera related to JO at New England College, 1983-1985 (Box 21:1325)
    - Copies of Ink - promotional articles about JO, 1982-1986 (Box 21:1326)
    - Materials for baseball-themed poetry reading at RIT, includes correspondence by JO, Sam Abrams, 1984-1985 (Box 21:1327)
    - "Politics and the Literary Imagination in the 60s" - TSS of lecture given at Syracuse University, correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 21:1328)
    - Black Mountain College Revisited Materials - TSS of article by JO about BMC, promotional materials for reading by JO, 1984-1985 (Box 21:1329)
    - "Poetry of Place" conference materials (conference moderated by JO), 1985 (Box 21:1330)
    - Copies of JO's résumé, ca. 1985 (Box 21:1331)
    - Notes by JO on his cancer, possibility of his death, ca. 1985 (Box 21:1332)
    - New England College Alumni Bulletin - publication of poem, " For the Inauguration...", 1986 (Box 21:1333)
    - Materials for Elderhostel Summer Conference on Poetry of Place ( New England College), 1986 (Box 21:1334)
    - "Getting it Right" - article by Michael Joyce about JO, undated (Box 21:1335)
  - Ephemera -- Publications and Other Materials Retained by JO
    - Clippings and articles not related to JO, 1950-1964 (Box 21:1336)
    - Alternative Press Ephemera, 1962-1967 (Box 21:1337)
    - Copies of articles by Pete Hamill (friend of JO), 1969-1972 (Box 21:1338)
    - Clippings regarding death of Leon Seidel (owner of Lion's Head Restaurant, which JO frequented), 1968 (Box 21:1339)
    - Flyers and announcements not involving JO, ca. 1968-1969 (Box 21:1340)
    - Flyers for poetry readings not involving JO, ca. 1968-1969 (Box 21:1341)
    - Ephemera from South Street Seaport, ca. 1968 (Box 21:1342)
    - Book Catalogs and Advertisements, ca. 1969-1970 (Box 21:1343)
    - Flyers/ Announcements of local relevance to JO, ca. 1969-1970 (Box 21:1344)
    - TSS poems by others, including Gilbert Sorrentino, George Stanley, Howard Shulman, Sam Abrams, 1961-1962 (Box 21:1345)
    - Poems by others, including Gil Henderson, John Cowles, others, ca. 1960 (Box 21:1346)
    - Poems in TSS by others - Knox Burger, Daniel Murray, others, undated (Box 21:1347)
    - Galley proofs of The Butterfly by Michael Rumaker, undated (Box 21:1348)
    - Galley sets of Four Love Poems by Robert Creeley, ca. 1961? (Box 21:1349)
    - Poetry TSS - not identified, not by JO, undated (Box 21:1350)
    - "Poems for Joel" - spiral bound book of poems by students, 1985 (Box 21:1351)
    - Galleys for book of poems by Joe Early, with Fielding Dawson, 1961 (Box 21:1352)
    - Galleys from book of psychological essays (relevance?) [FRAGILE], undated (Box 21:1353)
    - Printing samples, typeface cards, ca. 1954 (Box 21:1354)
    - Printing and typesetting resources, pre-1966? (Box 21:1355)
    - Book on Linotype Press Operation (with inscription, addressee unknown), 1925 (Box 21:1356)
    - Two Reel to Reel Audio Tapes - no label or date, ca. 1960? (Box 21:1357)
  - [loose contents not foldered] (Box 22)
    - Box of 5 1/4" floppy disks - JO word processing files, ca. 1985
    - UMAX tape - "Buffalo State Presents Video Poetics II, Joel Oppenheimer, Allen DeLoach", 1983
    - Betamax Tape - The Great American Desert, 4/26/80, 1980
    - VHS tape - " Joel Oppenheimer Reading at the Maryland Institute, February 28, 1985"
    - VHS tape - Hall of Fame Special: Hoyt Wilhelm, ca. 1985?
    - VHS tape - " Joel Oppenheimer: Halley's Comet", ca. 1985?
    - VHS tape - "1984 Sophomore Literary Festival - University of Notre Dame" (JO reading)
    - VHS tape - JO reading at Merrimack High School with note), ca. 1985?
    - Loose Audio Cassette Tapes
      - "Happy Birthday, Joel, 1984"
      - "JO, talk for 20th C. Art Class, Spring 1982"
      - "Earliest Memories, 9/88", 1988
      - "Joel - Early Memories, Sept. 1988"
      - "Joel's Memorial, 12/3/88", 1988
      - "For Joel's Groundhog Day, Bob Creeley, Jan. 4, 1989"
      - " Joel Oppenheimer, 2/2/89" [tribute pieces], 1989
    - Box of Audio Cassette Tapes - Various readings and interviews with JO, ca. 1984
    - Box of Audio Cassette Tapes - Readings by poets other than JO - includes William Carlos Williams, Hilda Doolittle, Marianne Moore, Hayden Carruth, Denise Levertov, Robert Frost, others, undated
    - Box of Audio Cassettes - Recordings of "Poetry of Place" Conference organized by JO at RIT, April 25-26, 1985
- Series V: Unprocessed materials, undated, 1970-1987
  General note
  [Identified correspondence has been pulled from the boxes listed below and placed in Series I.]
  - Correspondence, 1971-1972, 1977-1978, 1980-1982 (Box 23)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 24)
  - Correspondence, 1976, 1978-1979, 1982 (Box 25)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1981 (Box 26)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1977, 1980, 1985-1986 (Box 27)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1980, 1985-1987 (Box 28)
  - Correspondence, 1983-1985, 1987-1988 (Box 29)
  - Correspondence, 1977, 1980, 1984-1987 (Box 30)
  - Correspondence, 1983-1984, 1986-1987 (Box 31)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1977, 1984-1985 (Box 32)
  - Correspondence, 1982-1984 (Box 33)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 34)
  - Correspondence, 1973, 1976, 1978-1979 (Box 35)
    [Boxes below contain correspondence and poetry submitted to JO as poetry editor of the Village Voice newspaper.]
  - Village Voice submissions, 1980 (Box 36)
  - Village Voice submissions, 1981 (Box 37)
  - Village Voice submissions, 1971-1975, 1980-1981 (Box 38)
  - Village Voice submissions, 1973-1974, 1980-1981 (Box 39)
    [Boxes 40-51 comprise mainly teaching materials, including student work and administrative documents, with some correspondence intermixed.]
  - Student work by D.W. Donzella, Shaun Farragher, Leo Connellan, Alan Ziegler, Michael Stephens, and others, ca. 1970-1976 (Box 40)
  - Student work by Brian McInerney, Martha Moffett, Joe Johnson, Frank Lima, and others, ca. 1974-1979 (Box 41)
  - Teaching materials (City College, New York), student work by Nancy Lee Meade, financial ephemera (bills), 1978-1979 (Box 42)
  - Teaching materials, New England College, 1983-1984 (Box 43)
  - Teaching materials, City College and New England College, 1974-1975, 1983-1984 (Box 44)
  - Teaching materials, with student work by D.W. Donzella, Charlotte Adler, and others, 1972 (Box 45)
  - Teaching materials, City College, student work by Shaun Farragher, Dan Gabriel, Kathleen Chodor, and Jim Mele, 1972-1976 (Box 46)
  - Teaching, "Second Westbeth Workshop," student work by Brian McInerney, Toi Derricotte, Harry Greenberg, Howard Levy, circa 1973-1975 (Box 47)
  - Student work by Sharyn Skeeter, Andrew Reinbach, Kathleen Chodor, ca. 1974-1976 (Box 48)
  - Teaching materials, New England College and Rochester Institute of Technology, ca. 1984-1985 (Box 49)
  - Teaching materials, City College, ca. 1971-1975 (Box 50)
  - Teaching materials, including files on JO's "Poetry of Place" conference at RIT; also includes TSS of The Oyster and the Wind (novel not by JO), 1984-1985 (Box 51)
  - Prose drafts, including TSS of Marilyn Lives!, and JO's unpublished book on Fatherhood; also some Village Voice columns, additional research materials for prose articles, undated (Box 52)
  - Prose drafts (possibly Village Voice columns), "Dossier Materials," news clippings, undated (Box 53)
    [Boxes below contain additional ephemera and materials retained by JO, including fliers, catalogs, news clippings, and financial records.]
  - Westbeth materials, pamphlets on health care, posters for productions of JO's play, The Great American Desert, undated (Box 54)
  - Fliers, announcements, and junk mail, ca. 1974-1975 (Box 55)
  - Outgoing correspondence by JO, correspondence, doodles, photocopy of thesis about JO, news clippings, undated, 1972 (Box 56)
  - Financial records, correspondence, Westbeth materials, teaching materials, 1973-1978 (Box 57)
  - Announcements and fliers, including announcements for poetry readings at St. Mark's Church, ca. 1971-1976 (Box 58)
  - Clippings, correspondence, notebooks, doodles, and folder marked "receipts 1978", undated, 1978 (Box 59)
  - Teaching materials, City College; baseball notes and ephemera, submissions to JO as Village Voice poetry editor, undated (Box 60)
  - Village Voice submissions; photocopies of Cid Corman/ Charles Olson correspondence; materials relating to poetry contest judged by JO, undated, 1979 (Box 61)
  - Press releases and correspondence from CAPS, CCLM, St. Mark's Poetry Project, other publications, undated (Box 62)
  - Spiral bound notebooks carried by JO - most are not dated, and contain addresses, notes, and doodles, as well as partial MSS drafts of poetry, undated (Box 63)
  - Publications, newsletters, some correspondence, ca. 1981-1983 (Box 64)
  - Correspondence, fliers, clippings of JO columns, multiple issues of The Four Star Puzzler, 1977, 1983 (Box 65)
  - Teaching materials, School of New Resources; clippings, student work, and envelope labeled "BMC at Bard, 1987", 1976, 1987 (Box 66)
  - Tear sheets of Village Voice columns by JO; New England College ephemera, undated (Box 67)
  - Several issues of Gallery magazine, news clippings, Evergreen State College Bulletin, 1972-1973, 1980-1981 (Box 68)
  - Publications, including Poets and Writers Newsletter, City College Catalog (1974-76), NY State Council on the Arts, Author's Guild, other newsletters, 1970-1976, 1984-1986 (Box 69)
  - Periodicals and books, including books on baseball, books on sex, and the North Carolina Wesleyan University Yearbook, undated, 1977 (Box 70)
  - Periodicals and book catalogs, ca. 1975-1982 (Box 71)
  - Proofs/ Galleys of books by others (possibly sent to JO as review copies), undated (Box 72)
  - Professional Correspondence, Teachers and Writers Collaborative, 1969 (Box 73)
  - Alternative Press Publications (folio size), ca. 1981-1987 (Box 74)
  - Uncorrected TSS of novel by Ann Fairbairn, undated (Box 75)
  - TSS returned from Bobbs-Merrill, including The Wrong Season, Fielding Dawson's A Great Day for a Ballgame, and other works not by JO, undated, 1976 (Box 76)